Hello,
Speaker 1: somebody. Before we start today's episode, I want to personally invite you to an Ask Me Anything over on Patreon. All you need to do is go over to patreon.com forward slash Hello, Somebody and become a member. And on September 24th, you can join me.
Speaker 2: Ask me questions about anything you want. Go ahead.
Speaker 2: And hop over there right now,
Speaker 1: patreon.com/hellosomebody.
Now, today's
Speaker 1: episode is so good, I sat down with Famous the Rapper. He's a proud father, an independent artist, and there's a big surprise in this one. So here
we go.
So,
Speaker 3: Famous, it's wonderful for you to be able to join us today. Your hip-hop name is Famous, but your birth name is Robin Lee Dorsey Jr. Yes, I'm a
Speaker 4: junior. You
Speaker 5: are a junior. I got a junior, too. Famous
Speaker 6: actually means Robin, the definition of it. Is
Speaker 5: that right? Yes,
Speaker 6: if you look it up. Famous means Robin.
Speaker 7: Famous means Robin. So you didn't just pull this name out because it was hip and cool. It has...
Speaker 7: deep meaning
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): it has deeper meaning to it yeah that's a beautiful thing so you were born in queens new york yes jamaica queens new york jamaica
Speaker 9: queens new york are you still in new york
yes i'm in
Speaker 9: new york i reside in queensbridge right now
Speaker 7: and what is it about you and this vocation this gift that god has given you why rap why hip-hop
I
Speaker 10: was into sports at first. The first sport I ever played was baseball. I used to live in Puerto Rico. Oh, wow. Yes, I lived in a few places other than New York,
like Puerto
Speaker 10: Rico, Connecticut, Virginia, Washington, D.C., and Florida.
Speaker 13: And you picked up your love for baseball in Puerto Rico?
Speaker 10: Yeah, I started off with baseball. My favorite sport is football, though. Okay. Football and basketball. I'm very talented at that, too.
Speaker 15: Well you multi-talented,
Speaker 7: got many talents. Hip hop is my passion,
Speaker 16: like I
have a
Speaker 16: real passion for that.
Speaker 7: And when did you know that this was your thing? You know, so often it's hard for people to find that thing that gives them life, that breathes life into them, that they would do even if they made no money ever. It's just their calling. When did you know that rap, hip hop, when did you know that was your calling?
Speaker 17: Late teenage years, because before I used to play with it and recite other people's lyrics and
Speaker 10: then change up the song, change up their song, put my own lyrics. I used to do it just for fun, like rap in the lunchroom in school and stuff like that. People used to tell me that you should take it serious because you're talented at it. At first, I didn't look at it like that because I was more focused on sports. But yeah, I have a passion for it. It's not about the money, it's not about that. I do it for the passion first.
-
Speaker 18: Passion first, money
Speaker 10: second,
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): totally. - I feel a lot of people now, they don't take time to put the creativity into their craft.
Speaker 20: Like they
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): don't put, like I put a lot of effort into it. Like I read books to put in my rhymes, everything. Read dictionaries
Speaker 21: to find new words to
put in.
Speaker 22: It's very clear that you put a lot of effort into this vocation, this gift of yours, which leads me to something
Speaker 23: else that it is important that even though people are gifted, you got to put some effort towards the gift. And that's really what you're saying.
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): And I try to make my music relatable too. I want people to actually feel the music. I feel like that's...
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): missing right now.
Speaker 24: Well, music is
the
Speaker 7: universal language, they say. So you know what? You're bringing up for me two of my favorite songs by you. Obviously, I came to get
Speaker 3: to know your gift through
Speaker 3: Somebody who's close to me, my brother.
Speaker 13: Yes, I spoke to him. I actually spoke to him yesterday. You did. Yeah, we keep in contact often. Very good brother, very good brother. Yes, he is. Yeah, we talk. I appreciate him. I tell him every day I appreciate him. Every
Speaker 22: morning we talk and he told me every morning his wife has to wake up to your music because he's waking up to your music. He
Speaker 7: told me the same thing
yesterday. So
Speaker 7: two songs that I really enjoy for myself.
Speaker 7: "Daddy's Little Girls."
Speaker 26: - Yeah. - I see a lot of me inside the actions. Inside I'm asking how I can keep 'em away from life distractions. So they can go in situations knowing the right reaction. - And "Drunk With Jesus."
- I just feel
Speaker 27: like I'm chosen. I'm
chosen. -
Speaker 27: Okay.
Speaker 28: - So I want to start with "Daddy's Little
Speaker 7: Girls," a tribute to your three daughters?
Speaker 29: - Yes, three daughters.
Speaker 7: Zyviana, Avani, and Lana.
Speaker 7: I could feel, not just through the words
Speaker 30: you were saying, "All I have in this cold world is me and my girl." All I have in this cold world is me and my girl. It's just me and my girl. Obviously, your baby girl inspired the song.
Speaker 29: That's also the reason why I do music for them. I want to provide them a better life.
How
Speaker 12: did you set out to start to think of putting the words of that song together? They
were
Speaker 22: your inspiration, but you were very clear about the world is cold and
Speaker 7: how you wanted them to. And I'm paraphrasing. I'm giving you my interpretation of the song and you tell me you wrote it. You're the creator. But my interpretation was this was a song to instill and reinforce for your baby girls that you as their father, they really are your first loves.
Speaker 7: You love them. They are a creation. They are a gift to you. That they are beautiful and the world is going to see them that way. You even put in some remarks about how, you know, the boys got to beat them back basically. That their worth, you wanted them to know their intrinsic worth outside of another man or woman loving them. That number one, you love them. That's first and foremost. And you wanted them to know their value and you saw them as a gift.
Speaker 7: That's how I interpreted the song.
It
Speaker 4: is like that. And I want them to know that they love-- I tell my daughter that they're beautiful every day and I love them. I make sure I say that every time I see
Speaker 10: them, I tell them I love them, Daddy loves you. I want them to know their worth, too, that love come from within, not
outside. So
Speaker 10: I want them to know their worth in this world also, as long as they have parents that love them. But the words just flowed out. The words is already in me because of the love for my daughters. So it's already-- it was easy to make
Speaker 13: that song.
Speaker 22: You also talk about how you want to give them the world and that they also kind of change.
Speaker 12: The views about
women
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): was
Speaker 12: inspired by them.
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): Yes, yes. Because before I used to have many women in my life, like irresponsibly. Like the man I used to be, I wouldn't want my daughters to be with that. Now that I'm grown, I've grown a lot now that I have daughters.
Speaker 12: Evolution is a beautiful thing and to be able to have that kind of self-reflection is beautiful too.
Speaker 21: Yeah, and I'm going to be an example but because I'm the first person, I'm the first man they love. So, I want to be that example for them.
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): Amen. To see what a man is supposed to
be like.
Speaker 22: Yeah, you took the words right out of my mouth. You are the first man that they love and so they will reflect and also their value comes from knowing that love from
you.
just
Speaker 22: a beautiful song i certainly encourage anybody whether it's a mother or father but if you have daughters to really play this song that famous created it's a love song to your
Speaker 34: daughters it
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): really yes it is and i feel like like the world needs that today too because a lot of fathers missing out there in their child's life and i think that's the biggest like one of the biggest problems in like the urban community too it's like single motherhood and i think that's the plague in the black community
Speaker 22: Women do take a lot upon themselves. Black women, I believe, and I need to go back and double check this stat, but
Speaker 12: I think it's 75% of black households or so are led by single mothers.
Speaker 22: Now, it is very sad. Now, being a single mother or being the custodial parent doesn't necessarily mean that the father
Speaker 35: is not engaged in some way, but the burden of being that custodial parent is so heavy on black women.
It
Speaker 10: could be mentally draining on a woman, too. Oh, yeah. And it has a very bad effect on a child growing up.
Speaker 37: Yes, I agree. We need
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): more fathers back in the home. They're being misguided by other things, by media, by music, by just other things. And
they got a
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): lot of impressionable minds, too.
They
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): try to do stuff to fit in with the wrong crowd, just to look cool
Speaker 12: or... - Definitely need that kind of guidance and black women need relief. So it would be good. You know,
Speaker 22: there are a lot of surrogate dads, you know, out at uncles, people who children may not necessarily be their biological children. They pour into those kids,
Speaker 12: whether it's a teacher or a coach or someone from a church or a mosque. So I thank God. I just want to give a shout out to the fathers out there. Black fathers get a bad rap all the
time.
yes i
Speaker 12: want to shout out the good ones because there are some good ones and there are some black men who have stepped up to help uh commute their own their
Speaker 39: community yes that's good it's a good thing we need
Speaker 3: that it's a beautiful thing now leads me to my next song drunk with jesus
Speaker 26: i dress quick headed to the local spot to sip something i get there sit slumped in the chair i started with shots but cardi on rocks dizzy everything around me just stops i'm bugging out That's how I see the original song.
Speaker 26: I'm
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): drunk by myself, and he can drive in the car, just using the drunken stage or whatever. So I wanted to flip that and make my own type of song, original from that. And I've decided to make Drunk With Jesus.
It's just
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): basically, the song is me being
Speaker 17: drunk with Jesus, me having a conversation with Jesus. But basically, the stuff that we're
Speaker 10: taught in the Bible and stuff.
how
Speaker 10: the world is today, how it's totally opposite of that. Like, I feel like the world today is more corrupted than ever. It's like Sodom and Gomorrah, it's like Bob along right now. Can things change? Like, how can I play my part, you know, to make change in the world? I try to do my part through
Speaker 39: music. And that
Speaker 22: is a gift. In that song, when Jesus is talking to you, I mean, you're having this conversation about frustration and about what's happening in the world and the whole
Speaker 7: notion
of
you
Speaker 7: know, has nature run its course? You know, is this it? You know,
why is
Speaker 7: all these bad things happening in the world? And pretty much Jesus is saying this stuff has to happen, has to run its course until I return. You know, I'm like, yes! 'Cause I'm a church girl. So, you know, this song spoke to me on many levels. So pretty much the chaos and the pain, the ups and the downs and the turnarounds, like all of these things
or,
the
Speaker 7: yin and the yang, all of these things are necessary to happen for his
Speaker 43: return.
I'm
Speaker 4: just looking for answers. That's basically it. I'm looking for answers and how can I do my part?
Speaker 22: Yeah. I wish more of us asked how we could do our part. And then stay on your purpose. In that song, it was not get caught up in everything that's happening around you so much so that you're knocked off your purpose.
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): Yes, I think that everybody needs to focus on their purpose. I think that's the main thing people need to focus on what their purpose in life
is. And
Speaker 22: to know what it is, first you got to understand what it is. Yes, you got to
Speaker 10: understand that, yes. You got to understand yourself. That's why you got to learn yourself. A lot of people don't know who they
are.
Speaker 22: True that.
I
Speaker 22: really I really truly enjoyed that that song I must have I've listened to that song at least 10 times so hopefully
Speaker 44: that's one of my favorites
Speaker 22: actually good by the time we talk again I might have it memorized yeah
I really like that song yeah I
Speaker 45: think it's I think
Speaker 7: it's creative it is it's deep people can relate yeah one of their
Speaker 7: religious or not, I believe that there's a lot for everybody in both of the two songs that I really like. And I know that you have so many others, but I wanted
Speaker 12: to pick my favorite.
And
Speaker 36: when I do my music, I try not to be like too preachy. I try to still keep the entertainment value
Speaker 10: in it. Yeah. I don't want to come off too preachy 'cause I could, but I don't want to do that 'cause it won't be entertaining. Duke's probably boring. So I try to throw little bits and
Speaker 47: pieces of wisdom
Speaker 47: into it and drop jewels on it and you can get you know what you take out of it
Speaker 48: now who who influences you besides your daughters who are the other influencers in your life
as far as
Speaker 47: the music goes my my biggest influence was naz naz and jay-z they're probably
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): my biggest influence i like the storytelling from them
and i
Speaker 49: can relate
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): to them because we come from the same parts the
Speaker 7: expression of african americans and our ancestors i mean hip-hop is an amalgamason of all of that the blues -
Speaker 50: With the Jansen, yeah.
- Yeah, all of them.
Speaker 50: at right it's not just the rap and it's DJing it is dancing it's graffiti yeah
Speaker 7: it's all of it educators it's like it's a cultural movement but it is very much rooted in our experience in America pre the name of hip-hop I mean I can see it in the dance and the way we express ourselves throughout history
and even
Speaker 7: going back to the continent itself
So
Speaker 46: we go old school in the 70s and the 80s, you know, Sugarhill Gang comes to mind. Rapper's Delight. But I'm also thinking about one of my favorite songs, totally dating myself, but the double Dutch bus rolling down the
Speaker 7: street.
Speaker 7: You know, those kinds of things where it had these messages. It was fun. It was teaching, as you laid out. Not too preachy, but it also had lessons and messages. So we got our old school. And then I guess we would call the next phase of the '80s, like the mid '80s into the '90s. Some experts say that that is the new school hip-hop, where you got Run-D.M.C.
Speaker 46: and L.L.G., Raquel, Big Daddy Kane, Salt-N-Pepa.
Speaker 46: Coogee rap, yes, public enemy, fight the power. It was very
Speaker 4: diverse, like late 80s, 90s. MC light, you know. Yes, MC light, Queen Latifah.
Speaker 35: Queen
Speaker 7: Latifah, yes. When I listen to those kinds of songs, it's very clear what the messaging is. Now when we come up into the
Speaker 46: 21st century, it's kind of hard to see the messaging anymore. Terrible. What are your
Speaker 17: thoughts about that? There is no message.
Speaker 17: Today's hip-hop is terrible.
Speaker 10: There's some. There's people like J. Cole, Kendrick, that still stick to the true, like the art form, but for the most part, music is terrible. There's no message, and I feel like everybody feel they can do it now. That's why. It's been so big that everybody wants to do it, and a lot of people can't, but they feel they can infiltrate it because they see so many people, like untalented people doing it, and they say, oh, well, I can do this too, so they use it more as a hustle instead of a passion.
Speaker 10: So, I think that's terrible. I think you should do it because you love to do it. Like anything you do, you should love to do it. You put your all into it. You shouldn't do it just for a means to make money or hustle. That's like the definition of a cultural vulture.
Speaker 52: Do you think that culturally that rap could ever move back to that?
Speaker 52: to the
Speaker 17: foundation or is it too commercialized? I think it could, but it's a problem because a lot of the people that we grew up listening to
Speaker 10: are backing up the trash music. That's the problem right there. They don't back up people that's true to hip hop, but I think they do it from a business standpoint, I guess.
Speaker 10: because i think that's what the younger people want to listen to now but for me my message is i just want people to relate to the music and i try to bring it bring it back to what it used to be well you
Speaker 22: know i'm going to continue to hold our hope with you that hopefully we can that's
Speaker 10: what i'm trying to do
Speaker 22: go backwards to go forward yes i
Speaker 10: would love to put on people more like me but i see some people
coming
Speaker 10: Like Griselda, you ever heard of it? No. Griselda,
Speaker 17: you kind of stick to the roots. They sound more like a Wu-Tang. Oh, I love the Wu-Tang. Yeah, Wu-Tang. There's like little
Speaker 13: bits and pieces coming back. I think it's slowly
Speaker 46: coming back. So you're not out there alone in trying to keep alive that old school vibe. Yeah. The roots and origins of hip-hop.
I
Speaker 17: wouldn't say old school. People tell me that. They hear my music just because I can rap. They call me old school. I feel it's more timeless than old school.
-
Speaker 17: Okay, well, let's go on and use toddler, but you know old school is...
Speaker 54: Yeah, I know, I know, Judy, I know what the name is. -
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): That means deep. - Yeah. - Not superficial, deep. - Yeah, no, vintage, classic. - Vintage, okay, we're gonna say vintage school.
-
Speaker 13: And what made you wanna do the podcast?
Speaker 13: You went from Bernie Sanders to hip-hop. Well, you know,
Speaker 7: I had a podcast before called "We The People," and I've been a news commentator. So I've always tried to be engaged in things that would allow me to give voice to people's hopes and their dreams. And so podcasting is just another way to do it.
Speaker 7: Absolutely. When I was on the campaign, had no time for this kind of stuff. I mean, that's when the whole hello, somebody was born. I was just inspired as I was giving my speech and I was looking out into the crowd. And I saw their passion because it was right after Senator Sanders had a heart attack. And this was our first rally after the heart attack. So everybody was just full of hope and really happy that he recovered. And because I come from, you know, call and response is a big deal in the art form.
Speaker 7: and I wanted people to feel what I was saying
and I
Speaker 7: wanted them to respond. I wanted them to let me know. So since I didn't know everybody's name out there, I was just inspired to say, "Hello, somebody." And so the crowd just started saying, "Hello, somebody." My love for hip hop, I'm an advantage of people like Tupac,
Speaker 7: definitely i mean absolutely love love love tupac i mean famous when i was on the floor of the senate as a state senator i would quote tupac on the florida senate my colleagues looking at me like i was crazy oh yeah we're gonna bring some urban poetry to the floor of the ohio senate got money for wars but can't feed the poor hello somebody yes
I
Speaker 7: mean, that was my thing. And I put him, you know, just as people always quote the founding fathers or the framers or this famous person or that famous person. A lot of times in our hip hop and our urban culture, people don't necessarily think that it is worthy of being quoted. They marveled at the fact that I was quoting Thomas Jefferson and Tupac Secure. You damn right. I did. It's relatable because when you do that, you
Speaker 57: can relate to the youth.
Speaker 7: That's it. I mean, it's a universal money
Speaker 7: for wars, but can't feed the poor. People can relate to that young and old, especially if you are poor and suffering. And so LL Cool J is my absolute favorite. You
Speaker 57: and your own brother, your brother said the same
Speaker 7: thing. Yes, yes. And maybe we kind of rubbed off on each other, but I have a whole playlist of LL Cool J for my workout. So when I'm running the treadmill or jumping rope or boxing on my boxing bag, as I visualize people who work my last damn nerves,
Speaker 7: i'm listening to i'm listening who's one of
Speaker 58: the greatest one of the greatest
Speaker 7: to ll and then as far as you know for deeper consciousness certainly his public enemy the tupac type killer mike michael render and i have become really good friends and i listen to him a lot too and he goes deep so i listen to him on his activist side you know his artist side as well but the run dmcs of the world
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): you know biggie mace yeah yeah those are not so much because
he's
he
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): talks about some of these issues
Speaker 22: too. - Yeah, yeah, he really does. And you're right, like the people, Kendrick Lamar and some of the others are picking up on some of that
Speaker 7: tradition. And it's a beautiful thing to see. I'm not a, I love a good beat, but I think you and I may have in common, words matter.
and
Speaker 7: so i need some substance the
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): most important thing they are i don't you need substance for your soul i mean it just can't be about that's what's missing today about the substance there's no content yeah let's get some substance for our soul let's
Speaker 17: get substance for our soul and so that's why when i pick my beats i want the beast that feeling to it come on
Speaker 10: i don't want the beast to just because most of the beast now is just it all sound the same no originality to it
Speaker 48: now
Speaker 48: I mean, people need to make money. There's nothing wrong with that, especially if nobody gets hurt. I
Speaker 7: don't believe that people should make money off of other people's misery. You know what? Music is a lesson. It's not only
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): its own language, but it teaches many lessons. - I think if they played more
Speaker 17: conscious music, I
Speaker 10: think more people would be conscious. - I agree with you. - 'Cause they play the same songs over and over. They get it stuck in your head. I feel like it brainwashes
the
Speaker 62: youth. - The best is yet to come for
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): you, sir.
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): Thank you. I really appreciate it.
Speaker 63: You are so welcome. It's an
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): honor to be on your podcast. All right, babies, you take good care, darling. All right, you too.
Speaker 2: It was so great having that dialogue with Famous. And you know what?
He did
Speaker 64: something spectacular for Hello Somebody. Oh, my God.
And I got
Speaker 2: to give a shout out to my brother because it was his idea. Don't tell him. Don't tell him I gave him a shout out.
to
Speaker 2: my little brother, who's bigger and taller than I am. But I am the oldest, baby. But yes, my brother had this idea and Famous
Speaker 1: came through. So I want you to listen intently to the Hello Somebody theme song, baby. This song,
Speaker 65: this rap, this art.
Speaker 65: Baby,
Speaker 66: we'll make you move and groove. Take a listen.
I believe it. I
Speaker 68: believe that the leader of this in the
Speaker 69: universe has
Speaker 70: given us two hands. One
to reach
Speaker 69: one to reach one to the city
Speaker 71: as we climb, we
climb. Yeah,
Speaker 72: change is coming. The pain is numbing. Try to shoot for the stars if you're going to aim for something. Embrace the love for your brother and sister. Unity's the mission brush. We need to puzzle this picture. Let's paint it up. Frame it up for the world to see. Hang the hatred up. Enough is enough is enough. Making changes
Speaker 72: And Turner, her voice is the truth, her wise words inspire the youth to keep their eyes on the roof. It's the end, never give up, keep conquering goals, to the I, intelligence, silver, wisdom is gold. Back to the end, now is your time, stay firm, don't fold, to the A, all you need is the three bones, that's what Granny said. Now I'ma make sure these words from Granny spread, for all of here, just give her your ear. She can take you to the promised land, I swear, world peace is what they fear. From Queens to Cleveland, Ohio, we here.
Speaker 72: Famous.
We will not be neutral.